Details

BY POUL ANDERSON

What could the Galactic coordinator do when politics forced him to find someone's favorite nephew a job? Earth, after all, was a small planet ...

THE MOST austerely egalitarian societies—and the League is a mature culture which has put such games behind it—soon learn they must cater to the whims of their leaders. This is true for the simple reason that a mind on whose decisions all fate may turn, has to function efficiently: which it can only do when the total personality is satisfied and unjarred. For Rasnagarth Kri the League had rebuilt a mile-high skyscraper. His office took up the whole roof, beneath a dome of clear plastic, so that from his post he could brood by day over the city towers and by night under the cold radiance of the Sagittarian star-clouds. It was a very long walk from the grav-shaft door to the big bare desk.

Harban Randos made the walk quickly, almost jauntily. He was young, only a thousand years old, plumpish and sandy-haired, dressed in the latest mode of his people, the Shandakites of Garris. His tunic glittered with starry points of light and his cloak blew like a flame behind him.

He reached the desk and remained standing. Kri had not looked up. The harsh face was intent over a bit of paper. Around him the sky was sunny, aircraft flittered in dragonfly grace, the lesser spires glowed and burned as they clawed at heaven, the city pulsed. For the man in the plain gray robe, none of it existed, not while he was looking at that one sheet.

After all, its few lines of text and paramathematical symbology concerned eight billion human lives. In another lifetime or so—say 10,000 years-—the consequences might well concern the entire League, with a population estimated at ten to the fifteenth power souls.

After an interminable minute, Kri scribbled his decision and dropped the report down the outgoing chute. Another popped automatically from the incoming slot. He half reached for it, saw Randos waiting, and withdrew his hand.

“Harban Randos, sir, by appointment,” rattled off his visitor. “Proposed agent-in-chief for new planet in Section 239762—”

“I remember now. Sit down.”

Kri nodded curtly. “Coordinator Zantell and Representative Chuing urged your qualifications. What are they?”

“Graduated in ’75 from Mime Psychotechnic Institute in the second rank. Apprenticeship under Vor Valdran on Polaris V, rated as satisfactory.” Damn the old spider! What did he think the Service was ... the Patrol?

“Polaris was a simple operation,” said Kri. “It was only a matter of guiding them along the last step to full status. The planet for which you have been recommended is a barbarous one, therefore a more difficult and complex problem.”

Kri sighed. “How much do you know of the situation on this one? —No, never mind answering, it would take you all day. Frankly, you’re only getting the job for two reasons. One, you are physiologically identical with the race currently dominant on the planet in question. We have no other qualified man who could be surgically disguised. All those I would like to appoint are tied up elsewhere with more important tasks. Two, you have the strong recommendation of Zantell and Chuing.

“Very well, the post is yours. The courier boat will take you there, and supply you with hypnotic instruction as to the details en route. You already know the Service rules and the penalties for violating them.

“I only wanted to see you for one reason ... to tell you personally what your job means. You’re a young man, and think of it as a stepping stone to higher things. That’s an attitude which you’ll have to rub off. It’s an insignificant planet of an undistinguished star, out on the far end of the Galaxy, with a minimum thousand years of guidance ahead of it before it can even be considered for full status. I know all that. But I also know that it holds more than a billion human creatures, each one fully as valuable as you and I, each one the center of his own particular universe. If you forget that, may the Great Designer have mercy on them and on you.

“Dismissed.”

Randos walked out, carefully energetic. He had been prepared for this, but it had still been pretty raw. Nobody had a right to speak to a free citizen of a full-status planet like that . . . like a not very trustworthy child. Damn it, he was a man, on the mightiest enterprise men had ever undertaken, and—

And someday he might sit behind that desk.

Kri allowed himself a full minute’s reflection as Randos departed. It was so tinged with sadness that he wondered if he weren’t getting too old, if he hadn’t better resign for the good of the Service.

He sighed, and a weary smile tugged at his mouth. You didn’t work many centuries in the Service without becoming an idealist and a cynic. An idealist who lived for the mission, and a cynic who knew when to compromise for the sake of that mission. Theoretically, Kri was above political pressures. In fact, when there was no obvious disqualification, he often had to give somebody’s favorite nephew a plum. After all, his funds and his lower echelons were politically controlled-—

He started, realizing how much time had passed and how many decisions had yet to be made before he could quit for the day. He bent over the report and dismissed from his mind the planet called Earth.

THE DOORMAN was shocked.

He was used to many people going in and out of the gray stone building, not only toffs and tradesmen but foreigners and Orientals and even plain tenant farmers. Benson & McMurtrie, Import Brokers, was a big firm and had to talk to all sorts. He’d served in India as a young fellow and considered himself broad-minded. But there are limits.

“ ’Ere, now! An’ just where d’yer think you’re going?”

The stocky, sunburned man with the tattered clothes and the small brass earrings paused. He had curly black hair and snapping blue eyes, and was fuming away on an old clay pipe. A common tinker, walking into Benson & McMurtrie cool as dammit! “In there, ould one, in there,” he said with an Irish lilt. “Ye wouldn’ be denyin’ me sight of the most beautiful colleen in London, would ye?”

“That I would,” said the doorman. A passing carriage stirred up enough breeze to flutter the tinker’s rags, flamboyant against the grimed respectability of Regent Street. “On yer wye before I calls a bobbie.”

“Sure an’ it’s no way to be addressin’ a craftsman, me bhoy,” said the tinker. “But since ye seem to be sharin’ of this Sassenach mania for the written word, then feast your eyes on this.” Out of his patched garments he produced a letter of admittance, dated two years ago and signed by McMurtrie himself.

The doorman scanned it carefully, the more so as McMurtrie was eight months dead, the nice white-haired old gentleman, struck down by one of these new-fangled autos as he crossed this very street. But it gave a dear description of Sean O’Meara, occupation tinker, and set no time limit.

He handed it back. “In yer goes, then,” he, conceded, “though why they—Nev’ mind! Behyve yerself is all I got ter sye.”

Sean O’Meara nodded gaily and disappeared into the building. The doorman scratched his head. You never knew, you didn’t, and those Irish were an uppity lot, a bad lot. Here Mr. Asquith was trying to give them Home Rule and the Ulstermen were up in arms about it!

Sabor Tombak had no trouble getting past the private secretary, who was a Galactic himself, but he sadly puzzled the lesser employees. Most of them concluded, after several days of speculation, that the tinker was a secret agent... it was well known that Benson & McMurtrie had enough financial power to be hand in glove with the Cabinet itself. They weren’t so far off the mark at that.

The inner office was a ponderosity of furniture and sepia, Tombak shuddered and knocked out his pipe. Usrek Arken, alias Sir John Benson—grandson of the founder, who had actually been himself—started. “Do you have to bring that foul thing in here?” he complained. “The London air is bad enough already without you polluting it.”

“Anything would be welcome as a counter-irritant to this stuff,” answered Tombak. His gesture included the entire office. “Why the Evil don’t you guidance boys get on orbit and guide the English into decent taste? An Irish peasant without a farthing in his pocket has better-looking quarters than this kennel.”

“Details, details.” There was a sarcastic note in Arken’s voice which did not escape Tombak. The word had somehow become a proverb in his absence.

“Better get hold of the boss and let me report,” he said. “I’ve got an earful to give him.”

“An eyeful,” you mean,” replied Arken. “Written up in proper form with all quantitative data tabulated, if you please.”

“Oh, sure, sure. Gimme time. But this won’t wait for—”

“Maybe you don’t know we have a new boss,” said Arken slowly.

“Huh? What happened to Kalmagens?”

“Killed. Run over by a bloody Designer-damned petroleum burner eight months ago.”

Tombak sat down, heavily. He hadl had a great regard for Kalmagens, born professionally—the Franco-Prussian business had been handled with sheerly beautiful artistry—and as a friend. He dropped into fluent Gaelic for a while, cursing the luck.

Then he shook himself and asked: “What’s the new man like?”

“Harban Randos of Garris. Young fellow, fresh out of his apprenticeship. A very good psychotechnician, but seems to think the psychotechnic laws will cover every situation.” Arken scowled. “And the situation right now is nasty.”

“It is that,” agreed Tombak. “I haven’t seen many newspapers where I’ve been, but it’s past time Kaiser Wilhelm was put across somebody’s knee.” He jumped back to his feet with the restless energy of two years tramping the Irish roads. “Where’s Randos now? Damn it, I want to see him.” Arken lifted his brows. “All right, old chap. If you really insist, I’ll call him for you, and then I’ll crawl under the desk and wait for the lightning to subside.”

He buzzed for the secretary and told him in English: “Send Mr. Harrison to me, please.” That was for the benefit of the non-Galactic employees. When the door had closed, he remarked to Tombak: “You know how complicated the secrecy requirement can make things. Bad enough to always have to look your Earth-age, and. officially die every fifty years or so, and provide a synthetic corpse, and assume a new face and a new personality. But when you’re at the top, and all the leading autochthones know you as an important man—Chaos! We have to fob Randos off as a senior clerk, freshly hired for nepotistic reasons.”

Tombak grinned and tamped his pipe. He himself was in the lowest echelon of the 5000 Galactics serving on Earth, and refused to study for promotion. He liked being soldier and sailor and cowboy and mechanic and tramp, all to gather knowledge of how the Plan was progressing on the level of common humanity.

A plump, undistinguished form, in somber clothes that looked highly uncomfortable, entered. “You sent for me, sir?” The door closed behind Harban Randos. “What’s the meaning of this? I was engaged in an evaluation of the political dynamics, and you interrupted me just as I was getting the matrix set up. How many times do I have to tell you the situation is crucial? What the Chaos do you want now?”

“Sir Randos . . . Sabor Tombak, one of our field agents, just in from a survey of Ireland,” murmured Arken. “He has important new information for you.”

Randos did not bow, as urbanity demanded. He looked tired and harried. “Then file it and mark it urgent, for Designer’s sake!”

“Trouble is,” said Tombak imperturbably, “this is not stuff that can be fitted into a mass-action equation. This concerns individual people—angry people.”

“Look here—” Randos drew a ragged breath. “I’ll take time to explain to you.” His tone grew elaborately satirical. “Forgive me if I repeat what you already know.

“This planet wasn’t discovered till 1798, and it was three years before a mission could be sent. The situation was plainly critical, so much so that our men couldn’t take a century to establish themselves. They had to cut corners and work fast. By introducing technological innovations themselves, and serving with uncanny distinction in several countries’ armed forces and governments, they barely managed to be influential at the Congress of Vienna. Not very influential, but just enough to get a stopgap balance-of-power system adopted. Not enough to prevent the wave of antidemocratic reaction and the subsequent revolutions... but they did stave off a major catastrophe, and settled down to building a decent set of governments. Now their whole work is in danger.

“Kalmagens’ death threw everything into confusion,” went on Randos. “I suppose you know that. You fellows carried on as best you could, but the mass is not identical with the sum of the individuals concerned. There are factors of tradition, inertia, the cumbersome social machinery ... it takes a trained man to see the forest for the trees. Things have rapidly gone toward maximum entropy. An unstable system of checks and balances between rival imperialisms is breaking down. We have less than a year to avert a general war which will exacerbate nationalism to the point of insanity. I have to develop a program of action and get it into effect. I have no time to waste on details!”

“The Turkish-Italian war was a detail, of course,” said Tombak blandly.

“Yes,” snapped Randos, “Unfortunate, but unimportant. The Ottomans have had their day. Likewise this Balkan business.”

“Saw a paper on the way here. Sun Yat-Sen’s government is having its troubles. Are all those Chinese another detail?”

“No, of course not. But they can wait. The main line of development toward full status is here in Western Europe. It happened by chance, but the fact is there. It’s European civilization which has got to be saved from itself. Do you realize that Earth is only a century or so from atomic energy?” Randos took an angry turn around the office. “All right. I’m trying to work out a new balance, an international power alignment which will hold German ambition in check until such time as their Social Democrats can win an unmistakable majority and oust the Prussian clique. After that we can start shoving all Europe toward limited federalism. That’s the objective, sir, the absolute necessity, and your report had better have some relevance to it!”

Tombak nodded. “It does, chief, I assure you. I’ve talked with thousands of Irish, both in Ulster and the south. Those two sections hate each other’s intestinal flora. The southerners want the present Home Rule bill and the Ulstermen don’t. They’re being whipped up by the Carson gang, ready to fight . . . and if they do, the Irish-Irish are going to revolt on their own account.”

Randos’ lunar face reddened. “And you called me in to tell me this?”

“I did. Is civil war a detail?”

“In this case, Sir Tombak, yes.” Randos was holding back his temper with an effort that made him sweat. “A single English division could put it down in a month. But it would take all Britain’s and France’s manhood to stop Germany, and we’d have to drag in a dozen other countries to boot. The United States might get involved. And the USA is the main line after Europe, Sir Tombak . . . they have to be kept out of this mad-dog nationalism to lead the world toward reason when their day comes.” He actually managed to show his teeth. “I’ll forgive you this time on grounds of ignorance. But hereafter submit your reports in properly written form. The next time you disturb me with a piddling detail like Ireland, you’ll go back to Sagittarius. Good day!”

He remembered to assume a meek look just as he was opening the door.

There was a silence.

“Whoof!” said Tombak.

“Second the motion,” said Arken. "But I warned you.”

“I need a drink. Damn these masochistic British tavern hours!” Tombak prowled over to the window and looked gloomily down at the traffic. “Kalmagens was an artist,” he said, “and artists don’t worry about what is detail and what isn’t. They just naturally see the whole picture. This chap is a cookbook psychotechnician.”

“He’s probably right, as far as he goes,” said Arken.

Tombak shrugged, “Maybe. I dunno. I guess we’ll just have to wait and see.”

PETER MORTENSEN was born north of the Danevirke, but after 1864 his people were reckoned German, and he was called up in 1914 like anyone else. Men died so fast on the eastern front that promotion was rapid, and by 1917 he was a captain. This did not happen without some investigation of his background— many Schleswig Danes were not very glad of their new nationality —but Graf von Schlangengrab had checked personally on him and assured his superiors of his unquestionable loyalty. Indeed, the count took quite a fancy to this young man, got him transferred to Intelligence, and often used him on missions of the utmost importance.

Thus the official record, and in the 20th century Anno Domini the record was more than the man—it was the man. To Galactics such as Vyndhom Vargess and Sabor Tombak, it was convenient: records are more easily altered than memories, if you have the right gadgets. So Vargess was now von Schlangengrab and Tombak called himself Peter Mortensen.

Tombak, nee Mortensen, sat with a dozen men in a leading car of the sealed train. It was damp and chilly, they all huddled around a small stove. Beneath them, the wheels clicked on rain-slippery rails. Now and again the train whistled, shrill and lonesome noise across the graves of a thousand years of war. They held blue hands toward the stove, rolled cigarets, and talked among themselves. “Cold, it’s been a long time cold, and not enough fuel any more.

Sometimes I wonder what it ever felt like to be warm and dry.”

“Be colder than this in Russia, lad. I’ve been there, I know.”

“But no fighting this time, thank God. Just taking that funny little man toward St. Petersburg .. . why the devil’s he so important, anyway? Hauled him clear from Switzerland in his own special train, on orders of General Ludendorff, none less, one small Russian crank.”

“What say, Captain?” asked someone. “Are you allowed, now, to tell us why?”

Tombak shrugged, and the faces of peasants and laborers and students turned to him, lost between military caps and shoddy uniforms but briefly human again with simple curiosity. “Why is it, sir? Is he a secret agent of ours?”

“No, I’d not say that.” Tombak rolled himself a cigaret, and a corporal struck a match for him. “But it’s very simple. Kerensky has overthrown the Czar, you see, but wants to keep on fighting. This Ulyanov fellow has a good deal of influence, in spite of having been an exile for so long. Maybe he can come to power. If he does, he’ll make peace on any terms____ which is to say, on German terms. Then we’ll no longer have an eastern front to worry about.” Tombak’s leathery face crinkled. “It seems worth trying, anyhow.”

“I see, I see ... Thank you, Captain . . . Very clever—”

What Tombak did not add was that von Schlangengrab had been given the idea and told to execute it by a senior clerk in an English brokerage house, over an undetectable sub-radio hookup. This clerk, Mr. Harrison, had checked Galactic records on Ulyanov—whom Kalmagens had once met and investigated in London—and run a psychotechnic evaluation which gave the little revolutionary a surprising probability of success.

“Maybe then we can finish the war,” muttered a sergeant. “Dear God, it’s like it’s gone on forever, not so?”

“I can’t even remember very well what began it,” confessed a private,

“Well, boys—” Tombak inhaled the harsh wartime tobacco and leaned back in a confidential mood. "I’ll tell you my theory. It was the Irish who began it.”

“Ach, you joke, Captain,” said the sergeant.

“Not at all. I have studied these things. In 1914 there was a great deal of international tension, if you remember. That same year the Home Rule bill was so badly handled that it alienated the Ulstermen, who were egged on by a group anxious to seize power. This caused the Catholic Irish to prepare for revolt. Fighting broke out in Dublin in July, and it seemed as if the British Isle were on the verge of civil war. Therefore our General Staff decided they need not be reckoned with for a while, and—”

—And the Sarajevo affair touched off the powder. Germany moved in accordance with long-laid plans because she did not expect Britain to be able to fulfill her treaty obligations to Belgium. But Britain wangled a temporary Irish settlement and declared war. If the English had looked more formidable that year, the Germans would have been more conciliatory, and war could have been postponed and the Galactic plans for establishing a firm peace could have gone on toward their fruition.

“Captain!” The sergeant was shocked.

Tombak laughed. “I didn’t mean it subversively. Of course we had to fight against the Iron Ring. And we will conquer.”

Like Chaos we will. The war was dragging into a stalemate, neither side could break the other, not when Russia had gone under.

If Russia did make peace, Randos had calculated, then the stalemate would be complete. Peace could be negotiated on a basis of exhaustion in another year, and America kept out of the mess.

Privately, Tombak doubted it. On paper, it looked fine: the quantities representing political tensions balanced out nicely. But he had lived in America some twenty years ago, and knew her for a country which would always follow an evangelist Like Wilson—whose election had hinged on one obscure county in California. Randos assured him that the personality of the leader meant little ... it was a detail . , . but—

At any rate, the main thing right now was to get Russia out of the war, so that she might evolve a reasonably civilized government for herself. Exactly how the surrender was to be achieved, was another detail, not important. This queer, bearded Ulyanov with the bookish diction and the Tartar face was the handiest tool for the job, a tool which could later be discarded In favor of the democrats.

The train hooted, clicking eastward with Ulyanov aboard.

His Party name was Lenin.

TOMBAK had not been in New York for three decades. It had changed a lot, everywhere he saw the signs of a feverish prosperity.

On other planets, in other centuries, he had watched the flowering and decay of a mercantile system, big business replacing free enterprise. For certain civilizations it was a necessary step in development, but he always thought of it as a retrogression, enthroned vulgarity grinding out the remnants of genuine culture, the Folk become the People.

It was a brisk fall day, and he stepped merrily along through the crowds, a short sunburned broad-shouldered young man, outwardly distinguished only by a cheerfully serene air. Nor was he essentially different inside: he was a full human creature with human genes, who simply happened to have been born on another planet. His environment had affected him, balancing anabolism and catabolism so well that he had already lived 2000 years, training mind and body . . . but that didn’t show.

He turned off onto Wall Street and found the skyscraper he was looking for and went up to the sacrosanct top floor. The receptionist was female this time, a very pretty one: woman suffrage had eased the team’s problems by allowing them to use their wives apd girl friends more openly. For a moment he didn’t recognize her, the face had been changed. Then he nodded. “Hello, Varra. Haven’t seen you since . . . good Designer, since the Paris Exposition!”

“We had fun then,” she smiled dreamily, “Care to try it again?”

“Hmmm . . . yes, if you’ll get rid of that godawful bobbed hair and cylindrical silhouette.”

“Isn’t it terrible? Usrek ran a computation for me, and the Americans aren’t going to return to a female who looks like a female for years.”

“I’ll get myself assigned back to Asia, then. Bali, for choice.” Tombak sighed reminiscently. “Just worked my way back from there— deckhand on a tramp steamer to San Francisco, then followed a harvesting crew across the plains, then did a hitch in a garage. Lots and lots of data, but I hope the boss doesn’t want it tabulated.”

“He will. Want to talk to him? He’s in the office now.”

“Might as well get it over with.” Tombak went through the door into the office of the president. It was Usrek Arken again, alias the financier Wolfe ... a name chosen with malice aforethought, for wolf he was on Wall Street. But what chance did brokers and corporations, operating mostly by God and by guess, have against a million-year-old science of economics? Once Randos had decided England was declining as a world power, Wolfe’s dazzling rise was a matter of a few years’ routine.

Arken was in conference with Randos, but both rose and bowed. The chief showed strain, his plumpness was being whittled away and even the best total-organismic training could not suppress an occasional nervous jerk. But today he seemed genial. “Ah, Sir Tombak! I’m glad to see you back. I was afraid you’d run afoul of some Chinese war lord.”

“Damn near did. If it hadn’t been for our Mongoloid agent in Sinkiang—well, that’s all past.” Tombak got out his pipe. “Had a most enjoyable trip but of course I’ve been out of touch with all the big event. What’s been happening?”

“Business boom here in the States. That’s the main thing, so I’m concentrating on it. Tricky.”

Tombak frowned. “Pardon me, but why should the exact condition of business in one country be crucial?”

“Too many factors to explain in words,” said Randos. “I’d need psychodynamic tensors to convince you. But look at it this way—

“Let’s admit we bungled badly in T4 and again in T7. We let the war break out, we let America get into it, and we underestimated Lenin. Instead of a republic, Russia now has a dictatorship as ruthless as any in history, and paranoid to boot; nor can we change that fact, even if the rules allowed us to assassinate Stalin. We hoped to salvage a kind of world order out of the mess: once American intervention was plainly unavoidable, we started the ‘War to end war’ slogan and the League of Nations idea. Somehow, though, the USA was kept out of the League, which means it’s a farce unless we can get her into it,”

Thanks for the “we,” thought Toinbak grimly. With the benefit of hindsight, he knew as well as Randos why the Russian Revolution and the Versailles peace had gone awry. Lenin and Senator Lodge had been more capable than they had any right to be, and Wilson less so . . . the poor man had been no match for practical politicians, and had compounded the folly with his anachronistic dream of “self-determination.” (Clemen- ceau had passed the rational judgment on that idea: “Mon Dieu! Must every little language have a country of its own?”) But individual personalities had been brushed aside by Randos as “fluctuations, details, meaningless eddies on the current of great historical trends.”

“We still have an excellent chance, though,” went on Randos. “I don’t quite like the methods we must use, but they’re the only available ones. Wall Street is rapidly becoming the financial capital of Earth, a trend which I have been strengthening. If finance can be maintained as the decisive power, within twenty years America will be the leader of the world ... no one else will be able to move without her okay. Then the time will be psychologically ripe for Americans to get the idea of a new League, one with armed force to maintain the peace. The Soviets won’t stand a chance.”

Tombak scowled more deeply. “I can’t argue with your math, Sir Randos,” he answered slowly, “but I got a hunch—”

“Yes? Go on. You were sent around the world precisely so you could gather facts. If those facts contradict my theories, then of course I’m wrong and we’ll have to look for a new approach.” Randos spoke magnanimously.

“Okay, buster, you asked for it,” said Tombak in English. He returned to Galactic: “The trouble is, these aren’t facts you can fit into mass-action equations. They’re a matter of, well, feel.

“Nationalism’s rising in Asia. I talked with a Japanese officer in Shanghai.. . we’d gotten drunk together, and he was a very fine fellow, and we loved each other like brothers, but he actually cried at the thought someday he’d have to take potshots at me.”

“The Japanese have talked about war with the United States for fifty years,” snorted Randos. “They can’t win one.”

“But do they know that? To continue, though—People, Western people, don’t like the present form of society either. They can’t always say why, but you can tell they feel uprooted, uneasy . . . there’s nothing about an interlocking directorate to inspire loyalty, you know. The trade unions are growing. If capitalism goes bust, they’re going to grow almighty fast.”

“Of course,” nodded Randos, unperturbed. “A very healthy development, in the right time and place. But I’m here to see that capitalism does not, ah, go bust. Mass unemployment—You know yourself how unstable the Weimar Republic is. If depression is added to all its other troubles, dictatorship will come to Germany within five years,”

“If you ask me,” exploded Tombak, “there’s too bloody damn much confidence around. Too many people are playing the stock market. It has a hectic feel, somehow. They’d do better to save their money for an emergency.”

Randos smiled. “To be sure. I’ll admit the market is at a dangerous peak. In this month, it’s already shown some bad fluctuations. That’s why Wolfe is selling right now, heavily, to bring it down.” Usrek Arken stirred. “And I still think, Sir Randos,” he muttered, “that it’ll cause a panic.”

“No, it won’t. I have proved, with the help of games theory, that—”

“Games theory presupposes that all players are quite rational,” murmured Tombak. “I have a nasty suspicion that nobody is.”

“Come, now,” chided Randos. “Of course there are non-rational elements. But this civilization is in a highly cerebral stage.”

“What you ought to do,” snapped Tombak, “is get away from that computer of yours and go out and meet some Earthfolk.” Frost congealed on Randos’ words: “That is your task, Sir Tombak. Please report your findings and stand by for further assignment. Now, if you’ll pardon me, I’m busy.”

Tombak swapped a glance with Arken and went out. He chatted for a while with Varra and made a date for the next evening: Thursday, October 24, 1929.

The flames jumped up, lighting their faces:  grimy, unshaven, gaunted by wind and hunger, but American faces. Tombak thought he had fallen in love with America. A Galactic had no business playing favorites, and it was perfectly obvious that in another hundred years Earth’s power center would have shifted to Asia, but something in this country suited him. It still had elbow room, for both body and soul.

Far off (but coming along the rails near the hobo jungle, a train whistled. Tombak wondered how many times, how many places, he had heard that noise, and always it meant more lonesomeness.

“I looked at the schedule in the station.” A thin man with glasses jerked his thumb at the town, a mile away. “Be a freight stopping at midnight, we can hop that one.”

“If the dick don’t see us,” mumbled Robinson. “They got a mean dick in this place.”

“I’ll handle him, If it comes to that.” Tombak flexed stumpy strong fingers. Maybe a Galactic shouldn’t take sides, but there were some people whose faces he enjoyed altering . . .

“Be careful, Jim,” murmured Rose McGraw. She leaned against Tombak with a pathetic possessiveness.

In a better age, he thought, she would have been somebody’s contented housewife, minding the kids in suburbia, not tramping over a continent in a ragged print dress, rain in her hair, looking for work ... any kind of work. Too late now, of course, at least till the war with Japan made jobs. But Randos had predicted Japan would not attack till early 1942, give or take six months, and he was usually right about such things. Almost six years to go. Of course, initially he had thought the Japanese would never fight, but contrary evidence piled up—

“Don’t worry about me,” said Tombak gruffly. He felt again the tugging sadness of the quasi-immortal. How many years on Earth, how many women, and with none of them could he stay more than a few months. Rose McGraw had to become a fading memory fast bound in misery and iron for the sake of her descendants a thousand years hence.

“Think Roosevelt’s gonna win?” asked Robinson. He mispronounced the name.

“Sure, Landon hasn’t got a prayer” The man with glasses spoke dogmatically; he had had some education, a long time ago.

“I dunno, now. Old man Roosevelt, he’s for us, but how many of us stay in one place long enough to vote?”

“Enough,” said Tombak. He had no doubt of the election’s outcome. The New Deal under one name or another was foregone, once the Depression struck. Hoover himself had proposed much the same reforms. Randos had not even had to juggle the country—through propaganda, through carefully planted trains of events—to get FDR elected the first time. Tombak would be able to return from this trip and report that the changes were popular and that there was no immediate danger of American fascism or communism.

The main line of history, always the main line. Since the Rhineland debacle this year, war in Europe was not to be avoided, nor was war in the Pacific . . . Japanese pride and hunger had not been so small a factor after all. Tombak’s mind slipped to the Washington office where Randos was manipulating Senators and Brain Trusters.

“The important thing will be to keep the two wars separate. Russia will be neutral, because she has Japan to worry about, and Germany alone cannot conquer Britain. The United States can defeat Japan in about five years while the European stalemate is established. Then and only then must Germany and Russia be goaded into war with each other . . . two totalitarianisms in a death struggle, weakening as they fight, with America armed from the Japanese war and ready to step in and break both of them. After that we can finally start building an Earth fit to live on.”

An Earth which had so far gone from bad to worse, reflected Tombak. He didn’t deny the bitter logic of Randos’ equations; but he wondered if it was going to develop that way in practice. Roosevelt, who would surely run for a third term, had strong emotional ties— he could not see England fight alone, and he could make the country agree with him. And Hitler, now . . . Tombak had seen Hitler speak, and met enough Nazis. There was a streak of nihilistic lunacy in that bunch. Against all sound military principles, they were entirely capable of attacking Russia , . , which would mean the emergence of the Soviet Union, necessarily aided by America, as a victorious world power.

Well—

“Wonder if we’re ever gonna find a steady job,” said someone in the night.

“Ought to have a guy like Hitler,” said another man. “No nonsense about him. He’d arrange things.”

“Arrange ’em with a firing squad,” said Tombak sharply. “Drive men like Einstein out of the country. At that,” he added thoughtfully, “Hitler and his brown-shirted, brown-nosed bastards are doing us a favor. If this goes on, we’ll have more talent in this country than anybody ever had before,”

And if somebody had the idea of gathering it into one place, what would all that embittered genius do to Randos’ plans?

Bob Robinson shrugged, indifference clothed in faded denim. “To hell with it. I think the stew’s about done.”

HARBAN RANDOS’ eyes looked ready to leap out of their sockets. “No!” he whispered.

“Yes.” Usrek Arken slapped the papers down on the desk with a cannon-crack noise. “Winnis knows his physics, and Tombak and the others have gathered enough facts for him to work on. They’re making an atomic bomb!”

Randos turned blindly away. Outside, Washington shimmered in the heat of midsummer, 1943. It was hard to believe that a war was being fought ... the wrong war, with the issues irretrievably messed up, the Soviets fighting as allies of the democracies, Japan half shunted aside to make way for a Nazi defeat that would plant Russian troops in the middle of Europe . . . and meanwhile gnawing away Nationalist China, weakening the nation for communists who had only made a truce and weren’t even respecting it.

“They’re able to,” said Randos huskily.

Tombak nodded. “They’re going to,” he said.

“But they don’t need—”

“What has that got to do with it? And after the uranium bomb comes the thermonuclear bomb and— Write your own ticket.” Tombak spoke flatly, for he had come to like the people of Earth.

Randos passed a shaking hand over his face. “All right, all right. Any chance of sabotaging the project?”

“Not without tipping our hand. We could blow up the works, of course . . . fake a German operat5ion . . . but after the war, when they go through German records__”

“Vargess can handle the records.”

“He can’t handle the memories Not the memories of thousands of people, intrinsically just as smart as you and I.” Tombak bit his pipe-stem and heard it crack. “Okay, Randos, you’re the boss. What do we do next?”

The chief sat down. For a moment he shuddered with the effort of self-control, then his body was again disciplined.

“It will be necessary to deal firmly with the Russians, force them to agree to a stronger United Nations Organization,” he said. “Churchill already understands that, and Roosevelt can be persuaded. Between them, they can prepare their countries so that it’ll be politically feasible. The West is going to have a monopoly of nuclear weapons at the war’s end, which will be helpful . . . yes—”

“Roosevelt is not a well man,” declared Tombak, “and I was in England only a month ago and can tell you the people aren’t satisfied. They admire Churchill, love him, but they’re going to want to experiment with another party—”

“Calculated risk, of course,” said Randos. His confidence was returning. “Not too great.”

“Nevertheless,” said Tombak, "you’d better start right away to handpick those men’s successors and see they get exposed to the facts of life.”

“For Designer’s sake, leave me alone!” yelled Randos. “I can’t handle all those miserable little details!”

RASNAGARTH KRI did not want to spend time interviewing a failure.

Nevertheless, a favorite nephew is a favorite nephew.

He hooded his eyes, and it was a glittering blankness which looked across the desk at Harban Randos and wretchedness.

“It is fortunate,” he said, “that an experienced man of your race was available to take charge. For a while I even considered breaking all the rules and letting Earth know the facts immediately—but at this stage of their society, it would only be a slower damnation for them, extinction is more merciful. Whether or not the new man can rescue the planet remains to be seen. If he fails, then of course the whole world is lost. At best, it has been retarded two centuries, and several million people are needlessly dead.”

Randos stiffened his lips, which had been vibrating, and answered: “Sir, you were getting my annual reports. If I was unsatisfactory, you should have recalled me years ago.”

“Every agent is allowed some mistakes,” Kri told him. “Psychodynamics is not an exact science. Furthermore, your reports, while quantitatively accurate, were qualitatively—lifeless. They conveyed nothing of the feel. Until the fact leaped out that nationalism and atomic energy had become contemporaneous, how could I judge?”

Feel! Randos thought of Sabor Tombak . . . the smug, pipe-sucking pig! He hoped Tombak would be killed; plenty of chance for that, in the next fifty or a hundred years of Earth’s troubles.

“I used the standard methods, sir,” he protested. “You have seen all my computations. What else could I do?’

“Well—” Kri looked down at his desk. “It’s hard to answer that. Let me just say that human nature is so complicated that we’ll never have a complete science of it. All we’ll ever be able to do mathematically is predict and guide the broad trends. But those trends are made up of millions of little individual people and incidents. To pervert an old saying, in government it is necessary to be able to see the trees for the forest. It takes an artist to know how and when to use the equations, and how to supplement them with his own intuitive common sense. It takes not only a technician, but a poet to write a report which will really let me know what’s going on.”

He raised his eyes again and said mildly: “It’s not your fault that you are neither an artist nor a poet. I take it you wish to remain in the Service?”

“Yes, sir.” Randos was not a quitter.

“Very well. I’m assigning you to a chief technicianship in my own evaluation center. Consider it a promotion, a reward for honest effort... at least, it’s a higher rank and salary. You may go.”

Kri thought he heard a gasp of relief, but returned to his papers.

One might as well face it, you can’t kick a favorite nephew anywhere but upstairs. The fellow might even make a good technical boss.

As for this planet called Earth, maybe the new man could salvage it. If not, well, it was only one planet.